{
  "q1": [
    {
      "question": "This war’s French theater included a victory for the Duc d’Enghien [”duke” don-GYEN] at the Battle\nof Rocroi [roh-CWAH]. The Bohemian phase of this war ended with the Battle of White Mountain and\nthe defeat of the Winter King. Wallenstein and the Count of Tilly served as Imperial generals during this\nwar, in which Gustavus Adolphus was killed. The Peace of Westphalia ended, for ten points, what war\nfought over religion in modern-day Germany that lasted from 1618 to 1648?",
      "answer": [
        "Thirty Years’ War",
        "Thirty Years"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "The first edition of this publication depicted Speaker Joseph Cannon. It was founded by Briton\nHadden and Henry Luce, and it has often depicted men with a red “X” on their faces after their deaths.\nThis publication named Albert Einstein the Person of the Century and declared “You” the Person of the\nYear in 2006. For ten points, name this magazine that is famous for featuring single people on its cover,\nfeaturing a bright red border.",
      "answer": [
        "Time Magazine",
        "Time"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "Margaret Thatcher claimed to have carried a copy of this man’s most famous work in her handbag\nat all times. This thinker rejects the “benevolence of the butcher, baker, and brewer” as the reason that\ndinner is expected and, in his most famous work, describes a metaphor about the unintended social\nbenefits of private, selfish actions as the “invisible hand.” For ten points, name this Scottish “Father of\nEconomics,” the author of The Wealth of Nations.",
      "answer": [
        "Adam Smith",
        "Smith"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This modern-day nation was dominated by the Chola Dynasty until its liberation by Vijayabahu I,\nwho re-established Buddhism. Its native Kingdom of Kandy was dominated by the Dutch and conquered\nby the British, who grew tea in their colony of Ceylon. The majority Sinhalese fought with the Tamil\nTigers on, for ten points, what island off the coast of India?",
      "answer": [
        "Sri Lanka",
        "Ceylon"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "The “Buena Vista Tract” in this city features streets named for Mexican War generals. To make room\nfor this city’s Civic Arena, many blocks of its African-American Hill District were demolished. This city’s\nPoint State Park preserves the site of a fort that was targeted by General Braddock in the French and\nIndian War. Fort Duquesne [do-kane] was built at the confluence of the Monogahela and Allegheny Rivers\nin what is now, for ten points, what city in western Pennsylvania?",
      "answer": "Pittsburgh"
    },
    {
      "question": "Rather than initially perform this action, Kantaro Suzuki decided to respond to an ultimatum by\n“killing it with silence,” or mokusatsu. Commemorations of this action are held on August 15th and\nSeptember 2nd, recognizing either the Jewel Voice Broadcast or the official signing of documents on board\nthe USS Missouri. For ten points, name this event that ended fighting in World War II, four months after\na similar event in Germany.",
      "answer": [
        "the surrender of Japan in World War II",
        "surrender of Japan",
        "V-J Day",
        "V-J",
        "Victory in Japan Day"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "The production of this item names a group of 18th century nationalist revolutionaries in Italy.\nDuring the Industrial Revolution, the complete deforestation of Britain may have been prevented when\nblacksmiths replaced this item with coke. A companion company founded by Henry Ford produced this\ngood out of byproducts from its car manufacturing; that company is now called Kingsford. For ten points,\nname this hot-burning, wood-based, solid carbon fuel, commonly used in blacksmith forges and barbecue\ngrills.",
      "answer": "charcoal"
    },
    {
      "question": "This ruler resolved territorial disputes with Nader Shah by signing the Treaty of Resht and failed to\nform an alliance with William III. This man employed Patrick Gordon to capture Azov, which he later\ngave back to Ahmed III. He gave civil service a structured hierarchy via the Table of Ranks as part of an\neffort to reform the bureaucracy, and he disbanded the streltsy. The boyars lost both political power and\ntheir beards under the reign of, for ten points, what “Great” modernizing tsar of Russia?",
      "answer": [
        "Peter the Great",
        "Peter I"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This action has been successfully completed at Fra Mauro and the Ocean of Storms. The inability\nof the Zond program to finish a successful mission doomed Soviet efforts to even attempt this action. A\nspeech delivered at Rice University in 1962 claimed that America chooses to do this “and do the other\nthings not because they are easy, but because they are hard.” For ten points, name this accomplishment\nachieved by 12 Americans, first performed in 1969 by Buzz Aldrin and Neil Armstrong during Apollo 11.",
      "answer": [
        "landing on the Moon",
        "land on the Moon",
        "Moon landing",
        "sending peopel to the Moon",
        "going to the Moon"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "One war in this state began with an attack on Fort Myers, while another was triggered by the\nDade Massacre. This state, purchased as part of the Adams-Onis Treaty, was home to a Native American\ntribe led by Osceola that fought Winfield Scott and Andrew Jackson. The Seminole Wars were fought in,\nfor ten points, what southern U.S. state where the Spanish founded St. Augustine on the peninsula and\nPensacola on the panhandle?",
      "answer": "Florida"
    },
    {
      "question": "(TIEBREAKER BONUS QUESTION) In what 1973 conflict did Egyptian forces assault the Bar Lev line while Israel was\nobserved the Jewish day of atonement?",
      "answer": [
        "Yom Kippur Wa",
        "Yom Kippur"
      ]
    }
  ],
  "q2": [
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This man was nearly assassinated at the funeral of Warren Davis by Richard Lawrence. Under this\npresident, the US debt was paid off for the only time in history. This president had Levi Woodbury require\ngovernment land to be bought with gold or silver in the Specie Circular, and he created “pet” banks after\na veto. This man decried a “corrupt bargain” that he claimed cost him the Election of 1824. For ten\npoints, name this seventh President of the United States.",
        "answer": [
          "Andrew Jackson",
          "Jackson"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The Election of 1824 was decided in the House of Representatives when this Speaker threw his\nsupport to John Quincy Adams, who later appointed this man Secretary of State.",
        "answer": [
          "Henry Clay",
          "Clay"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "A god with this domain declared that Nut could not give birth on any day of the year, and was\nrepeatedly swallowed by Apep. Sekhmet and Bast were daughters of a god who represented this domain,\nwho was represented by the Wadjet. Under King Tut, worship related to this object, as represented by\nAten, reverted to reverence of Amun. For ten points, name this celestial body represented in Egyptian\nmyth by Ra and orbited by the Earth.",
        "answer": "the Sun"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This pharaoh, the father of Tutankhamun, established a temple at Amarna to promote the\nworship of the sun got Aten instead of Amun.",
        "answer": [
          "Akhenaten",
          "Amenhotep IV"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Marco Antonio Bragadin was flayed alive after surrendering Famagusta in the name of this city. This\ncity’s Arsenale [ar-seh-NAH-lay] was said to be able to produce a warship a day, helping it repel multiple\nOttoman invasions of Corfu. This city ruled over Crete after its leader, Enrico Dandolo, sacked Zara and\nagreed to provide transportation for the Fourth Crusade. For ten points, name this Queen city of the\nAdriatic, an Italian city known for its many canals.",
        "answer": [
          "Most Serene Republic of Venice",
          "Venice"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Enrico Dandolo was one of numerous Venetian rulers with this title, derived from the word for\nduke. These people were elected by 41 members of the Great Council.",
        "answer": [
          "Doge",
          "Doxe"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "The winning side of this match lit the cauldron in the opening ceremony of the 2002 Olympic Games.\nMarc Johnson tied this match, causing the other side to pull Vladislav Tretiak, its goalkeeper, after the\nfirst period. This game earned its name from a question asked by announcer Al Michaels in its final\nseconds. The winner of this match went on to defeat Finland to clinch the gold medal. For ten points,\nname this 1980 event in which the underdog United States defeated the Soviet Union in ice hockey at the\nOlympics.",
        "answer": "the Miracle on Ice,"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "When this sports magazine reported on the Miracle on Ice, its cover famously provided no\nheadline or explanation because, as the photographer noted, “everyone in America knew what happened.”",
        "answer": "Sports Illustrated"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "A man in this region claimed to be the Mahdi, the redeemer in Islam, and fought the Battle of\nOmdurman against the British. This region was the site of a coup by Omar al-Bashir. Chinese Gordon\ndied in this region while defending a city near the confluence of the Blue and White Nile. For ten points,\nname this geographic region of Africa south of Egypt, home to a country whose southern portion gained\nindependence in 2011, and whose remaining portion has its capital at Khartoum.",
        "answer": "the Sudan"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Since 2003, this western sub-region of Sudan has been the site of brutal violence, as Janjaweed\nmilitia have supported Omar al-Bashir’s forces.",
        "answer": "Darfur"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This battle began when the Arashi, which had previously attacked the submarine Nautilus, was\nsighted by enemy forces. Admiral Yamamoto’s plan for this battle went awry; his navy lost four of its\naircraft carriers while the U.S. only lost the Yorktown, a carrier damaged at the Battle of the Coral Sea.\nFor ten points, name this turning point of the Pacific Theater of World War II, a battle in the central\nPacific.",
        "answer": [
          "Battle of Midway",
          "Midway"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "After the victory at the Battle of Midway, American forces undertook this strategy of reclaiming\nspecific islands from the Japanese, which could then serve as bases from which they could attack the next\nisland.",
        "answer": [
          "island hopping",
          "leapfrogging",
          "jump",
          "hopping",
          "jumping from island to island"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This country’s ruler was greatly embarrassed by the revelation of Philipp zu Eulenburg’s [oy-len-burg’s]\nhomosexuality. This country sent a gunboat to its rival’s territory in Morocco, causing the Agadir Crisis.\nIts high command was led by Helmuth von Moltke, and it was accused of sending the Zimmerman\nTelegram, causing the United States to declare war on this country. Kaisers led, for ten points, what\nmember of the Central Powers, an empire that invaded France during World War I?",
        "answer": [
          "Germany",
          "German Empire",
          "Second Reich",
          "Kaiserreich"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The early 20th century German empire held a naval arms race with the UK, consisting primarily\nof building these “all big gun” steam battleships. This class of ship was named for a British vessel.",
        "answer": "dreadnoughts"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "The Atlantic provinces of this kingdom were lost to the Great Fulo. This kingdom was founded after\nthe defeat of Sumanguru at the Battle of Kirina and was succeeded by a dynasty led by Askia the Great.\nThis kingdom’s capital was Niani, the birthplace of its founder, Sundiata Keita. In 1324, one of its leaders\nwas so generous with his spending that he devalued gold in Egypt. For ten points, name this West African\nkingdom ruled by Mansa Musa.",
        "answer": [
          "Kingdom of Mali",
          "Mali"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Mansa Musa’s fame spread after he lavishly gave away gold and built mosques as he undertook\nthis traditional Islamic pilgrimage to Mecca.",
        "answer": "Hajj"
      }
    }
  ],
  "q3": [
    {
      "category": "PANAMA CANAL",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "French engineer whose company failed to build the canal and whose namesake tower rises above Paris.",
          "answer": [
            "Gustave Eiffel",
            "Eiffel Tower",
            "Eiffel"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Country that was forced to give independence to Panama so that the U.S. could build the canal.",
          "answer": "Colombia"
        },
        {
          "question": "Largest type of ship that transited the Panama Canal during World War II, used to launch fighter\nplanes at sea.",
          "answer": [
            "aircraft carriers",
            "carriers"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "U.S. President who signed the treaties returning the Panama Canal to Panama.",
          "answer": [
            "Jimmy Carter",
            "Carter"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Southernmost part of the Tierra del Fuego, which ships no longer had to round once the canal was\nbuilt.",
          "answer": "Cape Horn"
        },
        {
          "question": "Mosquito-spread disease that, like yellow fever, plagued canal construction sites.",
          "answer": "malaria"
        },
        {
          "question": "Panamanian dictator that the U.S. overthrew in 1989 after he threatened to nationalize the canal.",
          "answer": [
            "Manuel Noriega",
            "Noriega"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Country where China is planning to build an alternate canal through Punta Gorda.",
          "answer": "Nicaragua"
        }
      ],
      "prompt": "Name the..."
    },
    {
      "category": "ENGLISH CIVIL WAR",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "English legislature that fought against the king and was reduced to “Rump” size by Pride’s Purge.",
          "answer": [
            "Rump Parliament",
            "Parliament"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Island where Oliver Cromwell brutally suppressed Royalist soldiers from his base in Dublin.",
          "answer": "Ireland"
        },
        {
          "question": "Kingdom to the north of England that repeatedly intervened in the conflict.",
          "answer": "Scotland"
        },
        {
          "question": "Stuart monarch executed during the Civil War.",
          "answer": "Charles I"
        },
        {
          "question": "Title given to Oliver Cromwell after defeating the Royalists.",
          "answer": "Lord Protector"
        },
        {
          "question": "Document, originally written to protect 13th century barons, which was cited by the Petition of Right\nleading up to the War.",
          "answer": "Magna Carta"
        },
        {
          "question": "Army in which Cromwell served as cavalry leader during the Civil War.",
          "answer": [
            "New Model Army",
            "New Model"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Cromwell’s superior in that army, the victorious general at the Battle of Naseby.",
          "answer": [
            "Sir Thomas Fairfax",
            "Fairfax"
          ]
        }
      ],
      "prompt": "Name the..."
    },
    {
      "category": "THE CRADLES OF CIVILIZATION",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Age in which the first civilizations developed, often named for a material more primitive than bronze\nor iron.",
          "answer": [
            "Stone Age",
            "Stone",
            "Neolithic Age",
            "Neolithic"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Modern African country where civilization developed around the Nile River.",
          "answer": "Egypt"
        },
        {
          "question": "Modern Asian country where tea drinking developed and civilization grew around the Yellow and\nYangtze rivers.",
          "answer": "China"
        },
        {
          "question": "Civilization that developed around a river in modern Pakistan and included the city of Harappa.",
          "answer": [
            "Indus River Valley civilizaiton",
            "Indus"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Region between the Tigris and Euphrates rivers, in the eastern part of the Fertile Crescent in modern\nIraq.",
          "answer": "Mesopotamia"
        },
        {
          "question": "Civilization that developed in that Iraqi region whose cities included Uruk.",
          "answer": [
            "Sumeria",
            "Sumer"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Anatolian marauders who sailed the Mediterranean, rampaging early cities, but lost the Battle of the\nDelta on the Nile.",
          "answer": "Sea Peoples"
        },
        {
          "question": "Ancient proto-Greek civilization whose fall triggered the Greek Dark Ages.",
          "answer": [
            "Mycenaean culture",
            "Mycenae"
          ]
        }
      ],
      "prompt": "Name the..."
    }
  ],
  "q4": [
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Xu Bing used this art form to create the nonsensical Book From the Sky. Naskh and\nkufic are two forms of this art used by Muslim artists. This type of art was practiced on (20 pts) ",
        "tortoise shells in Shang dynasty China. Alcuin created one form of this technique known\nas the Carolingian miniscule. This technique is combined with (10 pts) ",
        "painting and illustration to\ncreate illuminated works like the Lindisfarne Gospels and Book of Kells as well as for transcribing the\nQuran. For ten points, name this visual art of elaborate decorative writing."
      ],
      "answer": "calligraphy"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This ruler chartered the Levant Company in an attempt to form a trade alliance with\nthe Ottoman Empire. This ruler supported the Netherlands through the Treaty of Nonsuch\nand attacked their enemy at Cadiz with the help of privateer (20 pts) ",
        "Francis Drake. During the\nTilbury speech, this ruler declared that she had the “body of a weak and feeble woman” but\nthe “heart and stomach” of a king while rallying her men against the (10 pts) ",
        "Spanish Armada. For\nten points, name this daughter of Anne Boleyn who succeeded her sister Mary I to become the “Virgin\nQueen” of England."
      ],
      "answer": "Elizabeth I"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) During one of these events, Barton Stone organized a large camp meeting at Cane\nRidge, Kentucky. During the second of these events, western New York was “burned over,”\nleaving no remaining population for this event to (20 pts) ",
        "convert. During the first of these\nevents, a speaker was inspired by the verse “Their Foot shall slide in due Time” to deliver (10 pts) ",
        "“Sinners in the Hands of an Angry God.” Jonathan Edwards, was a popular Reformed preacher\nduring the first of, for ten points, what religious revivals that swept through America in the 18th and 19th\ncenturies?"
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Great Awakenings",
        "First Great Awakening",
        "Second Great Awakening"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) In this work, a monk compares the tragedies of Lucifer, Hercules, Nero, and Julius\nCaesar, among others. Earlier in this work, an old hag notes that “sovereignty over their (20 pts) ",
        "husbands” is what women want most, as described by the Wife of Bath. This work was\nunfinished at its author’s death, including just 24 (10 pts) ",
        "stories after the General Prologue, which\nintroduces a group of pilgrims at the Tabard Inn on their way to visit the shrine of Thomas a Beckett, an\nArchbishop who was slain in 1170. For ten points, name this 14th century collection of stories written by\nGeoffrey Chaucer."
      ],
      "answer": "The Canterbury Tales"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man suppressed an insurrection by ordering a “whiff of grapeshot” on the 13th\nVendemaire. This man first achieved fame commanding the artillery at the Siege of (20 pts) ",
        "Toulon. This man attempted to reach British possessions in India by invading Egypt, and\nhe returned from exile on the island of (10 pts) ",
        "Elba in his Hundred Days, at the end of which he was\ndefeated by Gebhard von Bl¨ucher and the Duke of Wellington. For ten points, name this French emperor,\nwho was defeated at the Battle of Waterloo."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Napoleon I",
        "Napoleon"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This country’s president, Tiresias Simon Sam, was embarrassed by the German\ngovernment after the Luders Affair. The United States occupied this country after an\nuprising of the (20 pts) ",
        "cacos. After a massacre of this country’s whites, Jean-Jacques Dessalines\n[dess-ah-leen] named himself Emperor of this country in a revolution led by Toussaint\nLouverture. The (10 pts) ",
        "Duvalier family, led by “Papa Doc,” held a 20th century dictatorship in, for\nten points, what former French colony in the Caribbean that shares the island of Hispaniola with the\nDominican Republic?"
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Republic of Haiti",
        "Haiti"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This composer’s Adagio and Rondo was written for an ensemble that included Benjamin\nFranklin’s glass armonica. His final three string quartets were written for Friedrich Wilhelm\nII of (20 pts) ",
        "Prussia, and his eleventh piano sonata ends with an imitation of Janissary bands\nfrom the Ottoman Empire. The impresario Johann Peter Salomon gave this man’s forty-first\nand (10 pts) ",
        "final symphony the nickname Jupiter. K¨ochel [ker-kel] numbers are used to catalogue the works\nof, for ten points, what composer of the “Rondo alla Turca” and Eine Kleine Nachtmusik?"
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Wolfgang Amadeus Mozart",
        "Mozart"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) The first draft of this document was written by John Dickinson, who chaired an attempt\nto fix this document at Annapolis. The eleventh section of this document promised Canada\nautomatic (20 pts) ",
        "admission, should they wish to join the United States. This document left\nthe government unable to deal with (10 pts) ",
        "Shays’ Rebellion, since it denied Congress the power to levy\ntaxes or maintain an army. For ten points, name this predecessor to the U.S. Constitution, a document\nthat provided for a weak federal government."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Articles of Confederation and Perpetual Union",
        "Articles of Confederation"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) (TIEBREAKER EXAMPLE QUESTION) This man’s 4th Armored Division was able to stop an advance at the Battle of\nMontcornet. He wrote a book on how to modernize his nation’s military titled Army\nof the Future and ousted Henri Giraud for control of a resistance movement. As (20 pts) ",
        "President, this man pulled his nation out of the NATO command structure and\ndeveloped a nuclear weapons program, which carried out tests in (10 pts) ",
        "Algeria. For ten\npoints, name this first president of the Fifth Republic and leader of the Free French during World\nWar II."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Charles de Gaulle",
        "de Gaulle"
      ]
    }
  ]
}